A Finding Aid to the Robert Smithson and Nancy Holt Papers, 1905-1987, bulk 1952-1987, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Robert Smithson and Nancy Holt papers
1905-1987
bulk 1952-1987
Archives of American Art
Smithson, Robert
AAA.smitrobe
Archival Resource Key
67.3 Linear feet
The papers of sculptor, painter, and author Robert Smithson and sculptor, filmmaker, and earthworks artist Nancy Holt measure 18.9 linear feet and date from 1905 to 1987, with the bulk of the material dating from 1952 to 1987. Also included is Smithson's personal library of books, vinyl records, and magazine, measuring 48.4 linear feet. The papers consist of Smithson's biographical material; business and personal correspondence, much of it with artists; interview transcripts; extensive writings and project files; financial records; printed material; a scrapbook of clippings; holiday cards with original prints and sketches; photographic material; and artifacts. Also found are project files related to Nancy Holt's motion picture film Pine Barrens and her seminal environmental work of art Sun Tunnels, including a video documentary about Sun Tunnels.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The papers of Robert Smithson and Nancy Holt were donated by Nancy Holt in several accretions between 1986 and 2011.
Related Material
The Archives also holds several collections related to Robert Smithson and Nancy Holt, including an oral history interview with Robert Smithson conducted by Paul Cummings in 1972; an interview with Robert Smithson conducted by Tony Robbin in 1968; Robert Smithson letters to George B. Lester, 1960-1963; an oral history interviews with Nancy Holt conducted by Scott Gutterman in 1992 and Joyce Pomeroy Schwartz in 1993; and the Nancy Holt Estate records, circa 1960-2001.
Restrictions on Access
This collection is open for research. Access to original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C. Research Center. Researchers interested in accessing audiovisual recordings in this collection must use access copies. Contact References Services for more information.
Biographical Note
Robert Smithson (1938-1973) was a sculptor, painter, author, and lecturer who was known as a pioneer of land and earthworks art, based primarily in New York City. Nancy Holt (1938-2014) was a land artist, conceptual artist, and filmmaker. Smithson and Holt were married from 1963 until Smithson's death in 1973.
Born in Passaic, New Jersey, Smithson expressed an early interest in art, enrolling in classes at the Brooklyn Museum School and the Art Student's League in New York while still attending high school. Smithson's early works were primarily paintings, drawings, and collages. In 1959, he exhibited his first solo show of paintings at the Artists' Gallery in New York and had his first solo international show in Rome with the Galleria George Lester in 1961.
During the early to mid-1960s, Smithson was perhaps better known as a writer and art critic, writing numerous essays and reviews for Arts Magazine and Artforum. He became affiliated with artists who were identified with the minimalist movement, such as Carl Andre, Donald Judd, Nancy Holt, Sol LeWitt, Robert Morris and others. In 1963, Smithson married sculptor and filmmaker Nancy Holt and a year later started to create his first sculptural works. In 1966, Smithson joined the Dwan Gallery, whose owner Virginia Dwan was an enthusiastic supporter of his work.
Smithson's interest in land art began in the late 1960s while exploring industrial and quarry sites and observing the movement of earth and rocks. This resulted in a series of sculptures called "non-sites" consisting of earth and rocks collected from a specific site and installed in gallery space, often combined with photographs, maps, mirrors, or found materials. In September 1968, Smithson published the essay "A Sedimentation of the Mind: Earth Projects" in Artforum that promoted the work of the first wave of land art artists. Soon thereafter, he began creating his own large scale land art and earthworks.
From 1967 to 1973, Smithson's productivity was constant as he wrote, lectured, and participated in several solo and group shows a year, both at home and abroad. He explored narrative art as essay in "The Monuments of Passaic" and fully committed to his idea of visiting sites and using them as the basis for creating non-sites, Non-Site, Pine Barrens, (1968); incorporated and documented the use of mirrors at sites in Mirror Displacement, Cayuga Salt Mine Project (1968-1969); and created his first site-specific works through liquid pours of mud, asphalt, and concrete, including Asphalt Rundown (1969). In 1969, he also completed his first earth pour at Kent State University with his project Partially Buried Woodshed. Later that year, he created the sculptural artwork for which he is best known, Spiral Jetty (1969) on the Great Salt Lake in Utah. This was the first of his pieces to require the acquisition of land rights and earthmoving equipment, and would be followed two years later by Broken Circle and Spiral Hill in 1971.
On July 20, 1973, while surveying sites in Texas for the proposed Amarillo Ramp, Smithson died in a plane crash at the age of 35. Despite his early death, Smithson's writings and artwork had a major impact on many contemporary artists.
Nancy Holt began her career as a photographer and video artist. Today, Holt is most widely known for her large-scale environmental works, Sun Tunnels and Dark Star Park. Holt has also made a number of films and videos since the late 1960s, including Mono Lake (1968), East Coast, West Coast (1969), and Swamp (1971) in collaboration with her late husband Robert Smithson. Points of View: Clocktower (1974) features conversations between Lucy Lippard and Richard Serra, Liza Bear and Klaus Kertess, Carl Andre and Ruth Kligman and Bruce Brice and Tina Girouard. In 1978, she produced a film about her seminal work Sun Tunnels.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of sculptor, painter, and author Robert Smithson and sculptor, filmmaker, and earthworks artist Nancy Holt measure 18.9 linear feet and date from 1905 to 1987, with the bulk of the material dating from 1952 to 1987. Also included is Smithson's personal library of books, vinyl records, and magazine, measuring 48.4 linear feet. The papers consist of Smithson's biographical material; business and personal correspondence, much of it with artists; interview transcripts; extensive writings and project files; financial records; printed material; a scrapbook of clippings; holiday cards with original prints and sketches; photographic material; and artifacts. Also found are project files related to Nancy Holt's film Pine Barrens and her seminal environmental work of art Sun Tunnels, including a video documentary about Sun Tunnels.
Biographical material includes Robert Smithson's curriculum vitae, personal identification and medical documents, eight engagement/day planners Smithson and Holt maintained from 1966 to 1973, and Smithson's funeral register.
Correspondence is primarily with Smithson's family, friends, fellow artists, and business associates discussing personal relationships, proposed art projects, and exhibitions. Correspondents of note include Carl Andre, the Dwan Gallery (Virginia Dwan), Dan Graham, Will Insley, Ray Johnson, Gyorgy Kepes, Sol Lewitt, Lucy Lippard, and Dennis Wheeler. There is also substantial correspondence received by Holt upon Smithson's death in 1973, and between Holt and the Herbert F. Johnson Museum of Art regarding Smithson's retrospective exhibition in 1982.
There are nine interview transcripts with Smithson discussing his works and his general philosophy on art, and one transcript of the Andrew Dickson White Museum's Earth Art Symposium (1969) featuring the following artists: Mike Hiezer, Dennis Oppenheim, Robert Smithson, Neil Jenney, Gunther Uecker, Jan Dibbets, Richard Long, and Hans Haacke.
Writings are substantial and include 73 drafts of published and unpublished essays by Smithson on art, artists, and works in progress. The series also includes poems by Smithson, six notebooks containing notes and sketches by Smithson, and drafts of writings sent to Smithson and Holt by friends and colleagues, including Carl Andre, Terry Atkinson, Dan Flavin, Dan Graham, and Jack Thibeau.
Project files contain correspondence, project instructions, diagrams and sketches, research materials, photographic material, and maps related to over 50 of Smithson's artworks. These include concepts, proposed projects, sculptures, non-sites, and earthwork projects, including Spiral Jetty, Broken Circle, and Spiral Hill.
Personal business records include gallery related loan arrangements and receipts for miscellaneous art supplies. Financial records include tax forms and preparation documents, including cancelled checks, receipts, statements, and related correspondence.
Printed materials include books, clippings, and periodicals related to Smithson, either containing writings or sketches by him, or containing articles reviewing his work. There are also exhibition announcements and catalogs of Smithson's group and solo shows from 1959 to 1985.
The scrapbook contains clippings of Smithson's published articles from 1966 to 1973 with annotated shorthand notes.
Artwork consists of Christmas cards collaged by Smithson, and sketches by Smithson and Leo Valledor.
Photographic materials include prints and negatives of Smithson with friends, promotional Hollywood movie stills, and original prints and copyprints of other artists' artwork.
Artifacts consist of a paper bag silkscreened with a Campbell's soup can (Warhol), promotional buttons (N.E. Thing Co.), various organic materials, and two art kits.
Nancy Holt's papers consist of correspondence, a grant application, printed materials, and project files and audio visual material related to her motion picture film Pine Barrens (1975) and her seminal environmental work of art Sun Tunnels (1975).
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 14 series:
Missing Title
Series 1: Biographical Materials, 1905-1974 (Box 1; 14 folders)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1959-1987 (Boxes 1-2, OV 21; 1.7 linear feet)
Series 3: Interview Transcripts, 1966-1973 (Box 2; 11 folders)
Series 4: Writings, 1959-1975 (Boxes 2-3; 1.1 linear feet)
Series 5: Project Files, circa 1950s-1982 (Boxes 4-5, Boxes 17-18, OV 20, OV 22-26, OV 36, RD 28-30, RD 32-35; 6.5 linear feet)
Series 6: Personal Business Records, circa 1967-1970s (Box 5; 4 folders)
Series 7: Financial Records, 1962-1972 (Box 6-7; 0.4 linear feet)
Series 8: Printed Material, 1955-1985 (Boxes 7-11, Box 18, RD 31; 5.6 linear feet)
Series 9: Scrapbook, 1966-1973 (Box 11, Box 16; 0.3 linear feet)
Series 10: Artwork, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 11; 4 folders)
Series 11: Photographs, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 11, Box 18; 5 folders)
Series 12: Artifacts, circa 1950s-1970s (Box 11, Box 14, OV 19; 0.5 linear feet)
Series 13: Nancy Holt Papers, circa 1960s-1980s (Box 12-13, 15, OV 27, FC 37-38; 1.9 linear feet)
Series 14: Robert Smithson Personal Library (Boxes 39-87; 48.4 linear feet)
Existence and Location of Copies
The bulk of the collection was digitized in 2021 and is available on the Archives of American Art website. Items not digitized include duplicates, blank versos of photographs, and some publications for which only covers and relevant pages may be digitized. Additionally, financial records in Series 7, artifacts in Series 12, the Robert Smithson personal library have not been digitized. Some oversized material could not be digitized due to size.
Some of the film and video recordings in this collection have been copied for research access and are available in the Archives of American Art offices.
Interviews; Sketches; Scrapbooks; Earthworks (Art); Filmmakers -- New York (State) -- New York; Moving images; Documentary films; Women artists; Women filmmakers; Conceptual artists -- New York (State) -- New York; Dwan Gallery (New York, N.Y.); Insley, Will, 1929-2011; Holt, Nancy, 1938-2014; Lippard, Lucy R.; Johnson, Ray, 1927-; Kepes, Gyorgy, 1906-2001
- Biographical Materials, 1905-1974; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 14 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  The series consists of Smithson's curriculum vitae, a list of favorite things, an Art Students League class evaluation, vaccination records, a passport, a wallet, and eight engagement/day planners Smithson and Holt maintained from 1966 to 1973. Miscellaneous materials include an article on Charles Smithson and a photocopy of the front page of the New York Herald Tribune on the day of Robert Smithson's birth. The series also includes a funeral register and an artist's statement prepared by three unidentified friends upon Smithson's death.
  Arrangement note
  Materials are arranged chronologically within each folder.
  Existence and Location of Copies
  Series has been digitized in entirety.
  - Curriculum Vitae, 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - List, "My Favorites", 1952; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Art Students League Class Evaluation, circa 1950s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Passport and Vaccination Records, 1968-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Wallet, 1964-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Engagement Calendars, 1966-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes calendars for 1966, 1967, and 1968
  - Engagement Calendar, 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Engagement Calendar, 1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Engagement Calendar, 1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Engagement Calendar, 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Engagement Calendar, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Artists' Statement Following Smithson's Death, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Funeral Register and Cards, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Miscellaneous, circa 1905-1938; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Correspondence, 1959-1987; Series 2; Archival Resource Key; 1.7 Linear feet Boxes 1-2, OV 21
  Correspondence is primarily with Smithson's family, friends, fellow artists, and business associates discussing personal relationships, proposed art projects, and exhibitions.
  The series is arranged as 3 subseries:
  2.1: Family, 1959-1987
  2.2: General, 1961-1984
  2.3: Condolences, 1973
  - Family, 1959-1987; 2.1; Archival Resource Key
    Family correspondence consists of letters from Smithson to Nancy Holt and postcards from Smithson and Holt to Smithson's parents, Susan and Irving. Smithson's postcards to his parents detail his travels to Europe and updates on life and work projects in the 1960s-1970s. Holt's postcards tto Susan Smithson describe her travel and projects in the 1970s-1980s.
    - Holt, Nancy, circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Smithson, Susan and Irving, 1959-1961; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Smithson, Susan and Irving, 1971-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Smithson, Susan and Irving, 1974-1976; 1982-1987; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - General, 1961-1984; 2.2; Archival Resource Key
    General correspondence includes a handful of letters drafted by Smithson and Holt, with the bulk of the subseries comprising of letters from artists, art critics, collectors, museums, galleries, art organizations, universities, real estate brokers, and businesses.
    There is correspondence of note from the Dwan Gallery (Virginia Dwan) and from artist friends Carl Andre, Dan Flavin, Konrad Fischer, Dan Graham, Peter Hutchinson, Will Insley, Ray Johnson, Gyorgy Kepes, Sol Lewitt, Lucy Lippard, Toby Mussman, Claes Oldenburg, Dennis Oppenheim, Robert Wade, and Dennis Wheeler. There is also substatial correspondence between Holt and Robert Hobbs regarding the Herbert F. Johnson Museum of Art's retrospective Smithson exhibition in 1982.
    - A, Miscellaneous, 1966-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Includes letters from Vito Acconci
    - ACE Gallery, 1966-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - ACE Gallery, Oversized, circa 1966; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 21, Folder 1)
    - Andre, Carl, circa 1960s-1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Art International, 1967-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Art News, 1966-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Artforum (Leider, Phil), 1966-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - B, Miscellaneous, 1963-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 25)
      Includes letters from Jo Baer, John Baldessari, Bernd and Hilla Becher, and Donald Burgy
    - C, Miscellaneous, 1967-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
      Includes letters from Ted Castle, Rosemarie Castoro, Ron Cooper, and Bill Copley
    - Celant, Germano, 1969-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Centro de Arte y Comunicacion, 1970-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Columbia University, 1968-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - D, Miscellaneous, 1963-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 30)
      Includes letters from Jan Dibbets, Herbert Distel, Peter Downsbrough, and Thomas Downing
    - Dwan Gallery (Dwan, Virginia), 1966-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - E-F, Miscellaneous, 1965-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 32)
      Includes letters from Hamish Fulton
    - Fischer, Candace, 1968-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Fischer, Konrad, 1968-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Flavin, Dan, 1966-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - G, Miscellaneous, 1961-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Gemeentemuseum (Develing, Enno), 1968-1971; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - George Braziller, Inc., 1967-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Graham, Dan, circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Graham, Dan, 1965-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Guggenheim Museum, 1972-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - H, Miscellaneous, 1965-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 42)
      Includes letters from Hans Haacke, Tim Head, Doug Huebler, and Sam Hunter
    - Herbert F. Johnson Museum of Art, Cornell University (Hobbs, Robert C.), 1979-1980; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Herbert F. Johnson Museum of Art, Cornell University (Hobbs, Robert C.), 1981; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Herbert F. Johnson Museum of Art, Cornell University (Hobbs, Robert C.), 1982; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Herbert F. Johnson Museum of Art, Cornell University (Hobbs, Robert C.), 1983; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Herbert F. Johnson Museum of Art, Cornell University (Hobbs, Robert C.), 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Hutchinson, Peter, 1965-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - I, Miscellaneous, 1966-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 49)
      Includes letter from Robert Indiana, and letters from Institute of Contemporary Art
    - Insley, Will, 1966-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - J, Miscellaneous, 1966-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Johnson, Ray, 1965-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Junker, Howard, 1967-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - K, Miscellaneous, 1966-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Includes letters from Wolf Kahlen, Halasz Karoly, Kasper Konig, Bruce Kurtz, and Joseph Kosuth
    - Kepes, Gyorgy, 1968-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Kurtz, Bruce, 1971-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - L, Miscellaneous, 1966-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 4)
      Includes letters from Lallie Lloyd and Lee Lozano
    - Lewitt, Sol, 1966-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Lippard, Lucy, 1965-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Long, Richard, 1968-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - M, Miscellaneous, 1966-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 8)
      Includes letters from Joe Masheck and Robert Morris
    - McConathy, Dale, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Moderna Museet, 1984; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Museum of Modern Art, 1961-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Mussman, Toby, 1967-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - N, Miscellaneous, 1966-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - N.E. Thing Co., 1968-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - New York State Council on the Arts (Hunter, Sam), 1968-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Nova Scotia School of Art, 1970-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - O-P, Miscellaneous, 1968-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 17)
      Includes letters from John Perreault and Larry Poons
    - Oldenburg, Claes and Patty, 1967-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Oppenheim, Dennis, 1968-1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - R, Miscellaneous, 1968-1974; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 20)
      Includes letters from Ed Ruscha
    - Real Estate Related, 1968-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Real Estate Related, Oversized, 1968-1972; Archival Resource Key (Oversize 21, Folder 2)
    - Rhode Island School of Design, 1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Robbin, Anthony, circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - S, Miscellaneous, 1968-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 24)
      Includes letters from Harry Soviak, Petr Stembera, and Marjorie Strider
    - Sao Paulo Bienal (Kepes, Gyorgy), 1969; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Sharp, Willoughby, 1967-1970; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Smithson, Robert, 1961-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Sonsbeek, 1969-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - T, Miscellaneous, 1966-1967; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 29)
      Includes letters from Paul Thek
    - Ta' (Berg, H.M.), 1967-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - U, Miscellaneous, 1966-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - University of Utah, 1970-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - V, Miscellaneous, 1966-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 33)
      Includes letters from Jan van der Marck
    - Vollmer, Ruth, 1966-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - W, Miscellaneous, 1968-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 35)
      Includes letter from Mac Wells
    - Walker Art Center, 1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Wheeler, Dennis, 1970-1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Whitney Museum of American Art, 1967-1972; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Y, Miscellaneous, circa 1960s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Yale University, 1966-1968; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Unidentified and Illegible, circa 1960s-1970s; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Condolences, 1973; 2.3; Archival Resource Key
    Condolences consists of letters, cards, and notes of sympathy from family and friends addressed to Nancy Holt upon the death of Smithson.
    - A-C, Miscellaneous, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - D-H, Miscellaneous, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - I-M, Miscellaneous, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - N-R, Miscellaneous, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - S-Z, Miscellaneous, 1973; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 46)